<chapter><title>MRNet Components and Abstractions</title>
<para>
MRNet has two main types of components: <filename>libmrnet.a</filename>, a
library that is linked into a tool's front-end and back-end components, and
<filename>mrnet_commnode</filename>, a program that runs on intermediate nodes
interposed between the application front-end and back-ends. <filename>libmrnet.a
</filename> exports an API (See <xref linkend="mrnet_api"></xref>) that enables
I/O interaction between the front-end and groups of back-ends via MRNet. The
primary purpose of <filename>mrnet_comm</filename> is to distribute data
processing functionality across multiple computer hosts and to implement
efficient and scalable group communications. The following sub-sections describe
the lower-level components of the MRNet API in more detail.
</para>

<sect1><title>MRNet Communicators</title>
<para>
MRNet uses communicators to represent groups of network end-points. Like
communicators in MPI, MRNet communicators provide a handle that identifies a
set of end-points for point-to-point, multicast or broadcast communications. MPI
applications typically have a non-hierarchical layout of potentially identical
processes. In contrast, MRNet enforces a tree-like layout of all processes,
rooted at the tool front-end. Accordingly, MRNet communicators are created and
managed by the front-end, and communication is only allowed between a tool's
front-end and its back-ends, i.e. back-ends cannot interact with each other
directly via MRNet.
</para>
</sect1>

<sect1><title>MRNet Streams</title>
<para>
A stream is a logical channel that connects the front-end to the end-points of a
communicator. All tool-level communication via MRNet must use these streams.
Streams carry data packets downstream, from the front-end toward the back-ends,
and upstream, from the back-ends toward the front-end. Upward streams are
expected to carry data of a specific type allowing data aggregation operations
to be associated with a stream. The type is specified using a format string
(See <xref linkend="format_strings"></xref>) similar to those used in C
formatted I/O primitives, e.g. a packet whose data is described by the format
string "%d %d %f %s" contains two integers followed by a float then a character
string. MRNet expands the standard specification to allow for specifiers that
describe arrays of integers and floats. 
</para>
</sect1>

<sect1><title>MRNet Filters</title>
<para>
Data Aggregation is the process of merging multiple input data packets and
transforming them into one or more output packets. Though it is not necessary
for the aggregation to result in less or even different data, aggregations that
reduce or modify data values are most common. MRNet uses data filters to
aggregate data packets. Filters specify an operation to perform and the type of
the data expected on the bound stream. Filter instances are bound to a stream
at stream creation. MRNet uses two types of filters: synchronization filters
and transformation filters. Synchronization filters organize data packets from
downstream nodes into synchronized waves of data packets, while transformation
filters operate on the synchronized data packets yielding one or more output
packets.
</para>

<para>
Filters operate on data flowing upstream in the network. Synchronization
filters receive packets one at a time and do not output any packets until the
specified synchronization criteria has occurred. Transformation filters input
the group of synchronized packets, perform some type of data transformation
on the data contained in the packets and output one or more packets. A
distinction between synchronization and transformation filters is that
synchronization filters are independent of the packet data type, but
transformation filters operate on packets of a specific type.
Synchronization filters provide a mechanism to deal with the asynchronous 
rrival of packets from children nodes; the synchronizer collects packets and
typically aligns them into waves, passing an entire wave onward at the same
time. Therefore, synchronization filters do no data transformation and can
operate on packets in a type-independent fashion. MRNet currently supports
three synchronization modes:

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><emphasis>Wait For All</emphasis>: wait for a packet from every
child node,</listitem>
<listitem><emphasis>Time Out</emphasis>: wait a specified time or until a
packet has arrived from every child (whichever occurs first), or</listitem>
<listitem><emphasis>Do Not Wait</emphasis>: output packets immediately.
Synchronization filters use one of these three criteria to determine when to
return packets to the stream manager.</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>

<para>
Transformation filters combine data from multiple packets by performing an
aggregation that yields one or more new data packets. Since transformation
filters are expected to perform computational operations on data packets,
there is a type requirement for the data packets to be passed to this type of
filter: the data format string of the stream's packets and the filter must be
the same. Transformation operations must be synchronous, but can carry state
from one transformation to the next using static storage structures. MRNet
provides several transformation filters that should be of general use:
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><emphasis>Basic scalar operations</emphasis>: min, max, sum and
average on integers or floats.</listitem>

<listitem><emphasis>Concatenation</emphasis>: operation that inputs n scalars
and outputs a vector of length n of the same base type.</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<xref linkend="adding_filters"></xref> describes facilities a tool developer 
may use to add new filters to the provided set.
</para>
</sect1>
</chapter>
