<chapter><title>Introduction</title>
<para>
MRNet is a customizable, high-throughput communication software system for
parallel tools and applications with a master/slave architecture. MRNet reduces the cost of these
tools' activities by incorporating a tree of processes between the tool's
front-end and back-ends. MRNet uses these internal processes to distribute many
important tool activities, reducing analysis time and keeping tool front-end
loads manageable.
</para>

<para>
MRNet-based tools send data between front-end and back-ends on logical flows of
data called streams. MRNet internal processes use filters to synchronize and
aggregate data sent to the tool's front-end. Using filters to manipulate data in
parallel as it passes through the network, MRNet can efficiently compute
averages, sums, and other more complex aggregations on back-end data.
</para>

<para>
Several features make MRNet especially well-suited as a general facility for
building scalable parallel tools:
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><emphasis>Flexible organization.</emphasis> MRNet does not dictate
the organization of MRNet and tool processes. MRNet process organization is
specified in a configuration file that can specify common network layouts like
k-ary and k-nomial trees, or custom layouts tailored to the system(s) running
the tool. For example, MRNet internal processes can be allocated to dedicated
system nodes or co-located with tool back-end and application processes.
</listitem>

<listitem><emphasis>Scalable, flexible data aggregation.</emphasis> MRNet's
built-in filters provide efficient computation of averages, sums, concatenation,
and other common data reductions. Custom filters can be loaded dynamically into
the network to perform tool-specific aggregation operations. </listitem>

<listitem><emphasis>High-bandwidth communication.</emphasis> MRNet transfers data
within the tool system using an efficient, packed binary representation.
Zero-copy data paths are used whenever possible to reduce the cost of
transferring data through internal processes.</listitem>

<listitem><emphasis>Scalable multicast</emphasis>. As the number of back-ends
increases, serialization when sending control requests limits the scalability of
existing tools. MRNet supports efficient message multicast to reduce the cost of
issuing control requests from the tool front-end to its back-ends.</listitem>

<listitem><emphasis>Multiple concurrent data channels.</emphasis> MRNet supports
multiple logical streams of data between tool components. Data aggregation and
message multicast takes place within the context of a data stream, and multiple
operations (both upward and downward) can be active simultaneously.</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
</chapter>
